Hello!
你好
All right.
好吧。
Everybody welcome you have made it.
欢迎大家。
This is this is a Open Source Friday.
这里是开源星期五。
It's a Friday when we talked to opensource maintainers about the project they work on.
在这里，我们会讨论开源项目维护者正在维护的项目。
Sometimes we actually contribute to project, sometimes we build projects.
有时我们也为项目做贡献
And I'm super stoked to have Evan You here.
很高兴能邀请到尤雨溪来到我们的节目。
You: Hello!
尤：大家好！
Welcome.
欢迎
And just above your head you've got the Vue logo.
在你身后有 Vue 的 logo。
You: Yes.
尤：是的
Creator of Vue, maintainer , one of the maintainers of Vue as well.
尤雨溪是 Vue 的创造者，也是维护者之一。
And why don't you go ahead to introduce yourself and tell us why you here today?
那么就请你来自我介绍一下，告诉观众今天为什么你来到这里。
Sure.
好的
My name is Evan You.
我叫尤雨溪
and I am I,
我
I wrote Vuejs.
我写过 Vuejs
I'm the lead，team leader of Vuejs.
我是 Vuejs 的团队负责人
But in the past few months I'm also been working on a project called Vite.
但在过去的几个月里，我在做一个叫做 Vite 的项目。
which is what I'm going to be talking about today.
这也是我今天要讲的内容
So.
所以
Yeah.
是的
Vite was initially created somewhat related to Vue.
Vite 最初是与 Vue 相关的。
but now a kind of evolved into its own thing.
但现在已经有了自己的东西
And I'm kind of hoping that it can benefit developers,
我希望它能让开发者受益
especially frontend developers,
尤其是前端开发人员
not just few users,
不仅仅是少数用户
like all friend of developers.
就像所有开发者的朋友一样
Excellent,
很好
yeah,
是的
and it's funny,
它很有趣
cause I've definitely.
因为我已经肯定了
I know we chatted what was a last week for a completely different project,
我还以为我们上周聊了完全不同的项目
but I'd never heard Vite said out loud,
但我从来没有听过 Vite vit 的发音。
and I was called it Vite.
我之前的发音是 white
Yeah,
是的
A lot of people discovered that I don't know like I picked,
很多人发现我不知道我选的是
I picked the name.
我选了名字
It's actually a French word.
它实际上是法语单词
and French means fast or quickly,
Vite 在法语里的意思是快速迅捷
So.
所以
In fact,
事实上
It's cool too,
也很酷
to stick to its original pronunciation,
为了坚持它最初的发音
but we are now living in a dilemma because some people are like.
但是我们现在正处于两难的境地 因为有些人喜欢
If Vite is pronounced in the French way,
如果 Vite 的发音是法语的
then why isn't Vue pronounced in the French way?
那么 Vue 为什么不用法语发音呢
Cause Vue is actually a French word as well.
实际上 Vue 也是法语单词
So too bad.
太糟糕了
My own explanation is.
我自己的解释是
Just stick to whatever the author prefers.
只要坚持作者喜欢的就行了（就是尤大读什么就是什么）
I guess.
我猜
Yeah,
是的
Sorry.
对不起
I was just messing with the screens because they did see that somewhere.
我只是在摆弄屏幕因为他们确实在某个地方看到了
Oh,
哦
here we go a French word for fast,
是法语单词 表示 快
So all are the tips on how to speak French is right here in the README as well.
这些都是关于法语发音的提示就在 Readme里
So appreciate Evan doing that.
感谢 Evan 做了这些。
Excellent.
很好
So I guess what's the over, the high level of what would Vite is?
那么 Vite 是什么呢，从更高的层次上来看
Like fast is one of the key words,
就像"快速"是其中一个关键词
But like how would you describe it yet?
那么你怎么说？
It's actually a little hard, which is why every time people asked me to explain what it is like.
每次人们让我解释 Vite 是什么的时候，其实有点难度的
There's no really concise one sentence description of it.
没有办法用简单的一句话来描述它。
But if you want to make a comparison like if you have been using,
但是如果你想和你现在正在用的工具做比较
I think the closest thing in existence is Parcel, like the,
我想市面上 Vite 最接近的产品是 Parcel。
in terms of what it does and what a kind of affords you.
Vite 和 Parcel 提供的能力类似
But.
但是
Parcel bundler,
搜索 Parcel bundler
Google is help me today.
谷歌帮了我
Yeah,
是的
but obviously like the differences in how it's implemented,
但很明显，它在实现上是不同的
and in terms of how the dev server works is fundamentally different.
而且在开发服务器上的工作原理是完全不同的。
But in terms of what it does,
但就它的作用而言
you can think of it as something that takes some of your code and serve it.
你可以把 Vite 看作是将你代码运行起来的工具。
Yeah,
是的
I think it's really interesting because it's a dev server and a pre-configured bundler all in the same thing.
有趣的是，Vite 既是开发服务器也是预配置的打包器。
So like we can call it a frontend build tool.
我们可以称之为一个前端构建工具
But that's so generic, people just kind of ... It doesn't really explain anything in itself,
但是这种解释太普通了，人们还是不知道它是什么。
So I'm kind of struggling to come up with a really concise way to describe what it is,
我很难用一种非常简洁的方式来描述它
which is why,
这也是
like I kind of want to do this livestream because I think it's actually easier to just show people like what it does and how it works,
我想做这场直播的原因，因为我认为这种方式向人们展示它的功能和运作方式更容易
so you get a very direct understanding of all.
你可以很直接地理解所有的东西
This is what it is like.
它的样子
This is what Vite is.
理解 Vite 是什么
Yeah,
是的
I think we're actually.
我想我们实际上
So I do a lot of frontend myself.
我自己做了很多前端工作
I come from like a React background.
我是 React 背景
I've kind of some Vue projects too, on GitHub as well.
我也做过一些在 Github 上的 Vue 的项目
And I feel like we're going through an evolution that we're sort of seeing.
我觉得我们正在经历一场肉眼可见的革命。
I think we saw this five years ago,
我想我们五年前就看到了
probably longer than that,
也许会比那更早。
with like Webpack and how folks that's sort of adopted.
就像 Webpack 逐渐被接受。
That's type a bundler.
它是一种打包工具。
I might try to keep bundler is so you know as a one to one comparison.
我也许会把这些打包工具进行一一比较。
Because I know you're having trouble describing what this is.
因为我知道你很难描述是
But I think we are looking for an evolution.
但我认为我们正在寻找一种进化
I think we are now seeing even some of the hosting providers who are now adding all these bells and whistles and new features like we're ready for our next to the next wave,
我认为我们现在甚至看到现在一些主机服务商添加了所有些花哨的东西和新功能，就像已经为下一波浪潮做好了准备。
And that's why the stream is called next the next frontier,
这也是这股潮流被称为前沿的原因。
Alright, what is the steam called?
这股潮流应该叫什么？
I accept the title and I don't even know what it's called.
我知道它的称号,但我甚至不知道它叫什么。
But the next frontend tool tooling system generation.
它是下一代前端工具系统
That's what it was.
这就对了。
We are excellent.
我们很棒。
So what ... why Vite at this point in time?
那么为什么 Vite 在这个时间出现呢？
So I think Vite is essentially a ... a
我认为 Vite 本质上是 ...
Vite alongside you know snowpack, WMR, @web/dev-server.
Vite 以及像 snowpack、WMR、@web/dev-server 这类
I think we all come at a time where native ES modules has finally somewhat reached its close to being universally available.
我认为我们终于迎来了 ES 模块接近全局可用的时代了。
Finally,
终于。
If we disregard IE 11.
如果我们忽略 IE 11。
Then the latest version of all these major browsers all support native ES modules it now usable in GitHub as well.
现在所有主流浏览器的最新版本都支持原生的 ES 模块，而且现在 ESM 在 nodejs 中也可用了。
So the ecosystem is finally now starting to to do the sort of huge migration warrior.
生态系统现在终于开始做大规模的迁移战争了
Everyone is find OK,
大家发现，好了，
we have a standard module system now,
我们现在有标准模块系统
and it runs natively in the browser.
而且浏览器原生支持。
So all the a lot of the assumptions about tooling,
很多关于工具的假设
especially like if a tooling.
特别是如果工具
If you assume that all the code is going to be standard ES modules.
如果你假设所有的代码都是标准的 ES 模块
You can link up a lot of stuff.
你可以把很多东西联系起来
you can delegate a lot of stuff to browsers or some tools that just handle specific parts of the work flow faster than existing tools.
你可以将很多东西委托给浏览器或一些工具，它们只会比现有工具更快地处理特定的工作流程
And I think that's where this next generation of tools is going to be focused on.
我认为这就是下一代工具的重点所在
Is,
是
You know,
你知道吗
Finally,
终于
We have this native standard module system that's going to be somewhat universal,
我们有了原生的标准模型系统，它将在某种程度上普及。
And how can we sort of reimagined the tooling and just kind of take this opportunity to rethink how but what a clean slate or a faster version of what we are doing today could be like.
我们如何重新想象工具，如何利用这个机会重新思考我们今天正在做的事情，能够更加整洁快速。
Yeah,
是的
so speak of a fast,
说到快速
I know we prepared to share some screens to as well.
我们也准备好了屏幕共享。
I don't know if we want to jump in and give like high level of what to do when Vite and how to sort of get in get installed or involved with the project.
我不知道我们是否想要参与进来告诉大家我们如何安装 Vite 并且使用在项目中。
Ah,
啊
sure,
肯定的是
yeah,
是的
so I think I'm just going to start sharing my screen right now,
我想我现在就开始分享我的屏幕
so I think that's going to be there.
我认为应该有了。
All right,
好吧
so,
所以
yeah,
是的
so this is my screen.
是我的屏幕
If you want to get started,
如果你想开始
it's going to ask you to use GitHub and like use this init @vitejs/app.
你需要安装 nodejs，然后使用 init 命令初始化 @vitejs/app
But this is really for you know,
但真的是
for people who don't want to go through like many stuff,
对于那些想省事的人来说的。
but like to do what I'm not going to do that.
但是我不打算么做
So what I want to do today is just like.
我今天想做的是
Here is a fresh demo like I have an empty demo folder.
是全新的演示，我有一个空的文件夹
There's nothing here,
里面什么都没有
so I'm just going to do yarn add vite.
我使用命令： yarn add vite
There are -D vite.
有 -D 参数
Are you going to make this bigger?
要把它弄大点吗
So I just think started,
开始了
Ah, it doesn't scroll to the end.
啊？它没有滚动到最后
Why?
为什么？
Okay,
好吧
so and start pretty fast,
启动很快
So Vite is
Vite 是 ...
Let's take a look at the node modules.
让我们看一下 node modules 文件夹
It's 18 megabytes,
一共 18 MB
so it's also very small amount of modules that's actually being installed because we prebundle most of them to just make sure that installs faster.
实际安装的模块也非常少，因为我们预先将它们打包以确保安装速度更快。
This is why,
这也是为什么
compared to something like maybe create-react-app,
与 create-react-app 相比
you're probably going to have you guys probably going to see a noticeable differences in terms of just installing this thing itself by how faster,
你们会看到明显的区别就安装依赖本身而言， Vite 是更快的。
how much faster it is.
它快了多少
So now we have this thing here.
现在我们有了东西
Yes,
是的
I have these.
我有些
Let's just ignore all of the existing stuff I'm just going to put it in here.
我们忽略所有现有的东西 我把它放在里
you explain what we're looking at.
你解释一下我们在看
Here is well,
是好
these are the node modules.
这些是 node modules
Yeah,
是的
so this is just after you npm install or yarn add.
这些是你在执行 npm install 或者 yarn add 之后
and this is just what it creates just doesn't really matter.
所生成的文件，它们并不重要
So I'm just going to create a html file.
我要创建一个 html 文件
And say hello.
写一个 Hello
And then I'm going to, so you can do npx vite here.
你们可以在里执行 npx vite
case up your terminal when they're a little bit.
让你的终端往上一点
OK,
好吧
let's just move it here.
我们把它移到里
Then.
然后
Okay,
好吧
All I am going to just going here add a script.
我只需要在 package.json 里加一个 script 命令
So I'm going to say dev vite.
"dev" : "vite"
And then.
然后
Oh,
哦
yarn dev.
执行 yarn dev
So I started a dev server.
我启动了一个开发服务器。
Notice that I didn't do anything other than just running this.
注意我仅仅是添加了这个脚本，其他什么都没有做
so you can kind of think at the bare minimum think of it as a static file server.
所以至少我们可以把 Vite 看作是一个静态文件服务器。
You probably use something like serve or like a http static server,
你也许用过 serve 或者 http 静态服务器
whatever,
无论如何
like whatever your static files that were used to locally serve as a directory of static files right here,
就像你的静态文件在本地作为静态文件的目录一样
Just a vite command does that at the bare minimum.
至少一个 Vite 命令就能做到
So you see Hello.
大家可以看到 Hello
And that's the index.html being served.
这就是 index.html 的内容
So this I kind of like the so I use a lot by npx serve as a serve npm package.
是我喜欢的我经常用 npx serve
Yeah,
是的
OK,
好吧
So so far out of the box,
到目前为止
I can get a very similar command to serve the static files.
我可以得到非常类似的命令来为静态文件。
So it's a static file server,
它是静态文件服务器
but it's not obviously it's not meant for serving it in production right here.
但它显然不是用来生产的
does are these development stuff?
这些都是开发时的东西
So I edit and save and how we get like page reload out of the box.
我编辑并保存，发现无需任何配置，页面就能重新加载。
And with native modules.
用原生模块
With native ESM.
用原生的 ES 模块
you can do script type of module right so you can do.
你可以写 module 类型的脚本，你可以样做
You can either do import here in line.
你可以在这行使用 import
let's just do that actually main.js.
引入 main.js
yes,
是的
so it tells you failed to resolve a main.js because it doesn't exist.
报错告诉你无法解析 main.js 因为它根本不存在
So I'm going to create that here.
我将在里创建它
And.
并且
So reload the page.
重新加载页面
So make sure the console actually log hello.
确保控制台输出了 hello
so you also see vite connect thing,
你也可以看到 vite 连接的提示
which is our hot module replacement client.
这是我们的热更新客户端
That's being run,
正在运行
so if you add it to your file here,
如果你把它加到你的文件里
it also reloads the page.
它还会重新加载页面
And you can see this main.js file has been updated and reloaded so.
你可以看到 main.js 文件已经更新和重新加载了
This is not a real hot module replacement going on because this is just simply reloading the page.
不是真正的 hmr，因为只是重新加载页面
But it tracks all the things that's being import from your index.html.
但是它会跟踪 index.html 里面所有 import 的资源
To know that if you edit this file,
要知道，如果你编辑文件
I need to reload the page.
我需要重新加载页面
If you add other things,
如果你加上其他东西
I don't need to care about it.
我不需要关心它
And then some of the common stuff that we may want to do is.
我们想要做的一些常见的事情是
Like link to CSS files.
比如链接 CSS 文件
So let's just say style.css.
我们就创建一个 style.css 文件。
H1 color red.
H1 标签样式设置颜色为红色。
You can obviously just use a link so style.css.
显然可以用 link 标签链接到 style.css 文件
So notice here I can eh,
注意这里，我可以...
because it's an actual http server you can use like absolute paths,
因为它是http服务器 你可以使用绝对路径
here is just like what you'd expect.
和你想的一样
So we got this thing showing red on the screen,
屏幕上的内容变成了红色。
and if I edited here,
如果我在里编辑
you're you're mentioned about the absolute paths,
你你提到了绝对路径
somebody ask in the chat,
有人在聊天室提问
How to use of Vite from another folder than just root.
如何在不是根目录的其他文件夹使用 Vite？
How to use it from another folder?
如何从另文件夹使用它
Yes,
是的
I guess if you had like your CSS styles folder or I guess you could install the relative path to.
我想如果你有CSS样式文件夹或者你可以安装相对路径
Yeah,
你可以用相对路径
you can even ideas stuff.
你甚至可以有一些想法
It also follows all the npm node modules resolve algorithm.
它还遵循了所有的 npm node 模块解析算法。
OK,
好吧
which will show in a bit,
我们一会儿就会看到
but as you can see,
但正如你所见
like even there the simple link here and notice how,
就像简单的 link 标签，请注意
when I edit this thing,
当我编辑的时候
the page actually didn't reload.
页面实际上没有重新加载
It's hot updating the CSS in place.
它是热更新 CSS
So what what's making that work is awesome Vite magic server? Magic？
这是怎么做到的？是 Vite 的魔法吗？
Yeah,
是的
So Vite is doing the work of recording the relationship.
Vite 做了记录文件关系的工作
So one thing I kind of want to point out is like when we have a lot of users coming from webpack.
我想指出的一点是，我们大量的用户都是来自于 webpack
there are so used to thinking of this main.js as their entry point of application and HTML being the afterthought.
他们习惯于将 main.js 作为应用程序的入口点，而 HTML 则是事后的想法。
So Vite is kind of think of it as a server.
而对于 Vite 可以把它看作是服务器。
So your HTML is actually your entry point and feed Vite parses everything here to consider it a module graph entry.
因此 HTML 实际上是入口，Vite 实际上会解析里面的所有内容，把它当作是一个模块图的入口。
So style CSS, is considered part of the module graph.
所以 CSS 样式也被认为是模块图的一部分
This thing is turning into an inline module and which imports this main.js which is another module.
这里会变成内联模块，它导入的 main.js 是另一个模块 。
So notice how like index.html is actually the entry point to the application.
因此，请注意 index.html 实际上是应用程序的入口。
And it's kind of from there.
从那里开始
We construct the whole module graph of the application.
我们构建了应用程序的整个模块图。
Instead of like we're going from here,
我们不是从 main.js 开始
they will go in backwards and figure out what HTML should be.
之前他们会倒着去找出 html 是什么样子。
So that's kind of a thing.
这就是问题所在
A lot of people kind of have to sort of flip a switch in order to to get into Vite.
很多人需要按下开关才能开始适应 Vite
I think Parcel does this too, right.
我认为 Parcel 也是类似的。
So Parcel is kind of the pioneer of this concept of HTML being your entry and being part of the module graph.
Parcel 是将 HTML 作为入口和模块图的一部分概念的先驱。
and I think that's kind of the for web development.
我认为对于 web 开发者而言，
In particular.
在特定的
This is your stuff for me.
是你给我的东西
It's a more natural sort of mental module to work with,
是一种更自然的思维模式
but in a way right?
但在某种程度上 对吗
So what Vite does under the hood is we actually record these all these important relationships between the HTML and the CSS files.
Vite 背后的原理呢是我们记录了 HTML 和 CSS 文件之间的所有些重要关系。
So we can,
我们可以
we get to actually just update this linked CSS in place,
我们只需要更新链接的 CSS
and so that's right.
对吗？
This is not too much different from, say, a static file server.
这里和静态文件服务器没有太大区别。
So some of the things we also do out of the box is.
我们还做了一些开箱即用的事情
Let's say we have styled.module.css.
假设我们新建一个 style.module.css 文件。
I'm going to say er...
我要说...
What is the module keyword, We've actually not seen that before.
这个 module 关键字是什么，我们之前没有见过
So this is a convention I saw.
是一个约定
if you've worked with CSS modules,
如果你使用过 CSS 模块
it's kind of convention to name your files with this module.css.
用 .module.css 来命名文件是一种约定
And in Vite this is also a convention, so if you see, we see a file named like this,
在 Vite 里这也是一个约定， 我们看到这样命名的文件
and I'm going to say er..
这里要写...
.text
.text
Color
颜色
Red
红色的
And then I'm going to comment out this one.
我要把这块注释掉
And I'm gonna, say import classes from.
在这里 import classes from
style.module.css
style.module.css
Let's just log this,
我们把它打印出来
and as you can see,
如你所见
it gives you this Object with text in it.
一个带有 text 对象
So this is a class name,
这是类名
so I'm going to say.
这里写...
document.querySelector
document.querySelector
h1.className
h1.className
equals classes.text.
等于 classes.text
And now again red here,
现在这里又变回了红色。
so if you edit this thing here,
如果你编辑这里
it also reloads.
它还重新加载
So this is not hot module replacement,
不是置换的量
but but you get the idea right.
但是但是你的想法是正确的
so we have a lot of these big conventions here.
我们有很多约定
So imagine if you are.
想象一下如果你是
You previously had a project with plain webpack,
如果你之前有使用纯 webpack 的项目
and now you say I want to work with CSS modules,
现在你想使用 CSS 模块
you probably have to go through a guide to teach you what CSS loader is, what style loader is.
你需要通过指南来学习 CSS Loader 和 Style Loader。
Yes，I've definitely been that path.
是的，我之前就是这个学校路线。
Then you need to look at all the PostCSS configurations for to CSS loader add those loaders on webpack config again.
如果你想使用 PostCSS，你需要查找其对应的 CSS Loader 配置，然后再把这些 loaders 添加进 webpack 的配置中去。
You get what I mean right.
你明白我的意思了
So the idea of Vite is it's pretty opinionated.
Vite 的概念是很有主见的。
It has a lot of these kinds of things it's things built in and to sort of minimize the hoops you need to jump through to get certain things working.
它有很多内置的东西，它可以某种程度上减轻你做某些事情的障碍。
Similarly,
同样的
if you want to have custom PostCSS configs,
如果你想要自定义 PostCSS 配置，
so you just add post.config.js.
你只需要新建 postcss.cofig.js 文件
The export CSS config.
导出 css 配置
So this is.
是
This is similar to how you get the Tailwind CSS working.
这和你使用 Tailwind CSS 类似。
Because Tailwind itself is really a PostCSS plugin.
因为 Tailwind 本身就是 Post CSS 插件。
So if you configure,
如果你配置
you want to configure Tailwind with Vite.
你想要在 Vite 中使用 Tailwind
Ah,
啊
Let's see,
让我们看看
how can we get that working out?
我们怎么才能把它解决掉呢
Proudly be to go to Tailwind CSS.
自豪的去 Tailwind CSS 网站
And I'm going to look for Vite.
我要去搜索 Vite
I think there is a guide with Vite here.
我想里有指南有关于 Vite 的配置。
Yes,
是的
So why are you looking for that?
你为什么要找这个？
There's some some question that came in the chat room.
聊天室里有一些问题
Is there so similar, like create-react-app, is there like an eject feature, or as you just get Vite?
Vite 有没有和 creat-react-app 类似的 eject 特性？
So here's the thing like there's really no need to eject.
我认为真的没有必要 eject。
So Vite has its own configuration format,
Vite 有自己的配置格式
but it's not based on webpack, the idea is,
但并不是基于 webpack 的概念
CSS module is something that just works in Vite.
因为 CSS 模块只是在 Vite 中运行
there's really like if you want to configure it as you can,
如果你想要配置它，可以，
you just create a vite.config.js and you can say export defaults.
我们可以创建 vite.config.js 文件，在里面 export default
CSS modules.
css modules
then these options will be passed on to the PostCSS modules plugin so you can configure like,
这些选项会被传到 Post CSS 模块上，你可以这么配置
localsConvention.
localsConvention
To be camelCaseOnly if you want.
camelCaseOnly
If you use CSS modules you, you know what this does,
如果你使用过 CSS 模块，你就知道这个配置的作用。
but like most of these building stuff is also configurable.
但像大多数构建东西一样 也是可配置的
But the thing is.
但问题是
My personal opinion is because I've worked...
我个人的看法是因为我工作过 ...
We maintain Vue CLI for Vue right here , and the CLI is built on top of webpack.
我们维护了 Vue CLI，它是基于 webpack 的。
And we ship a lot of these stuff out of the box, infuse enthusiasm as well.
我们倾注了极大热情，把很多些东西从箱子里拿出来。
So we have in some way if you use Vite with Vue.
在某种程度上，如果你用 Vite 来驱动 Vue 项目
You almost scared identical feature set with Vue CLI in terms of what you can do with source code.
在操作源代码时，你可能会害怕使用 Vue CLI 相同的特性集合。
But we have to maintain a pretty complicated webpack config internally.
但我们必须在内部维护一个相当复杂的 webpack 配置。
And when people want to configure that it's typically quite involved.
当人们想要配置它时，通常是相当复杂的
An ideal with Vite is we essentially extracted.
Vite 的想法基本上是我们提炼出来的
A lot of these things that we know,
我们知道的很多事情
like users will need this in a typical project,
就像用户在典型的项目中需要
and also because,
还因为
over time,
随着时间的推移
a kind of in Vue CLI, we've come to these conclusion like this is kind of the sensible default.
我们在 Vue CLI 的维护中得出结论，是一种合适的默认配置。
Most people will want this,
大多数人都想要
so that's how are we going to present it in Vite by default as well.
我们也将它作为 Vite 的默认配置
And if there are certain things that you,
如果有一些事情
we know that users will want to customize,
我们知道用户想要自定义
we expose them via an option.
我们通过配置选项暴露出来。
Add the plugin system,
加上插件系统
Vite is also pretty flexible,
Vite 也很灵活
but I don't think we want to dig into that.
但我不认为我们今天要深入研究这个。
So I guess understanding these conventions,
我想理解了些惯例
like as I was talking about the bundlers and how we've sort of advanced now where everybody like new things to look forward to the next generation.
就像我刚才说的打包工具现在已经进步了，人们开始探索下一代的新东西。
I love the fact that there are strong opinions happening now in frontend JavaScript world.
我喜欢的事实是，现在有强烈的意见发生在前端 JavaScript 世界里。
because when you talk about like a webpack like I am triggered where I've definitely got to a point where I want to use this new things,
因为当你说到 webpack 的时候，我就想起了肯我想用新东西的时候
like Tailwind at the time,
就像当时的 Tailwind CSS
and but I don't know how to get it, like in my webpack config and there's sometimes some plugins some hoops I have to jump through, sometimes two different plugins that are competing against each other for space.
但我不知道怎么把它放进我的 webpack 配置里，因为有时候几个插件会相互冲突。
and sometimes I need both of them,
有时我需要两者
and I've sort of been burnt out enough about that situation.
我已经被那种情况搞得筋疲力尽了
But it sounds like in Vite, one of the steps is working on the box.
但听起来在 Vite 中，这些步骤都是开箱即用的。
Yeah,
是的
I think, it's so be more strong opinionated. I think it's just a different value proposition and different sort of where how at which level the tool want to live here.
我觉得 Vite 属于更"固执己见的"， 是不同的价值主张，工具想要在何种层次中生存也是不同的。
Webpack itself I think is still kind of very low level.
我认为 webpack 本身仍然是处在非常低的水平。
The downside is when you have such a low level abstraction and you want to allow all the higher level features to be configurable in user space.
缺点是当处于这么低的抽象程度，但还希望允许所有更高级别的特性都可以配置，
The complexity just explodes,
复杂性就会爆炸
whereas if you,
而如果是你
if the tool comes in and say,
如果工具进来说
hey,
嘿
I just want to be opinionated.
我只是想"固执己见"，
so I can manage much more for the user and because the tool gets to manage all these things together so the tool gets to sort of work.
我可以为用户管理更多的东西，因为工具把这些东西聚合在了一起协同工作。
All your systems is somewhat smoother because you have more control at the tooling layer,
所有的系统都更加流畅，因为在工具层有更多的控制
instead of forcing the user to figure out all of these, how to get plugging feature B to be compatible with feature B on that,
而不是强迫用户去弄清楚所有，比如如何让功能 A 与功能 B 兼容
and I think it's not necessarily saying like I think it's actually a miracle that you can make all these things work with webpack just like looking at all the plugins and loaders that you put together by.
我认为你可以让所有的 loaders 和 plugins 与 webpack 放到一起工作简直是个奇迹。
But you know,
但你知道
I think we come to the conclusion that most users don't really want to deal with that.
我认为我们得出的结论是，大多数用户都不想面对种情况。
So if the tool can sort of already handled most of these stuff in an opinionated way for them,
如果工具已经能够以一种"固执己见"的方式为他们处理些东西
they are happy to sort of just follow along,
他们很乐意跟着我们走
and I think that takes some too,
我想也需要一些
because,
因为
like we as an ecosystem, as the community we need,
作为生态系统和社区也需要
we needed something to pave the way, like webpack.
我们需要一些像 webpack 的工具来铺路
then we try to put all these things together on top of webpack.
我们尝试在 webpack 的上层，
and then we realize,
我们意识到
okay.
好吧
We finally come to the sort of almost a shared convention like how we deal with CSS.
我们最终达成了比如关于于如何处理 CSS 的约定，
How would you deal with certain types features right?
如何处理类型的功能。
So if you look at things across,
如果你从另角度看
like create-react-app or Vue-CLI or Next.js.
像 create-react-app or Vue-CLI or Next.js
A lot of stuff that is shared, right.
很多东西都是大家共享的，不是吗。
They were doing a lot of similar stuff on top of webpack.
他们在 webpack 之上做了很多类似的事情。
So I think we've finally reached his harm.
我想我们终于找到了他的弱点
Where most users almost take some of these as sort of granted,
大多数用户几乎认为其中一些是理所当然的
they think.
他们认为
Oh,
哦
it's natural that I am able to import CSS.
使用 import CSS 是很自然的，
It's natural that I am able to just use PostCSS out of the box,
可以直接使用 PostCSS 也是自然的。
so I think Vite is in some way.
我认为 Vite 在某种程度上
it's like,
就像
OK.
好的
If that's what people are used to already,
如果人们已经习惯了
then we can sort of just go directly to provided out of the box.
我们就可以直接提供开箱即用的功能。
And so question,
我们来看看提问。
so we just saw you do a bunch of commands with Vite.
我们刚刚看到你用了很多 Vite 命令。
How about like,
怎么样
How do we compare this with the Vue CLI they are going to be working together eventually,
Vite 和 Vue CLI 最终会一起工作吗，
or do they work together today?
还是它们现在就已经一起工作了呢？
They don't work together today because Vue CLI is still webpack based.
它们现在不一起工作，因为 Vue CLI 现在仍然是基于 webpack 的。
So in the long term,
从长远来看
we're probably want to eventually migrate Vue CLI to be Vite based.
我们最终想要将 Vue CLI 迁移到基于 Vite 上来。
So Vue CLI in terms of scope is a little bit higher level than Vite.
Vue CLI 在范围上比 Vite 更高，
because it also includes scaffolding.
因为它还包括脚手架
It has more built in scaffolding.
它有更多的内置脚手架
It has this.
它有
It's plugin system which I don't know if we want to keep if we eventually migrate Vite.
还有插件系统，我不确定迁移到 Vite 之后，这个系统是否还要保留。
But Vue CLI lives at a higher level where its view specific has more scaffolding and also gives you more opinionated integration with like test runners and all this stuff.
但 Vue CLI 处在更高的层次，它有更多脚手架，也给你更多约束性的集成，如测试运行器和很多其功能。
So it's a more complete solution,
所以 Vue CLI 是更完整的解决方案。
So.
所以
It's interesting,
有趣的是
yes,
是的
so Vite is like higher level than webpack but lower level than Vue CLI, somewhere in between.
Vite 层次高于 webpack，但低于 Vue CLI，它介于二者之间。
Got it,
明白了。
yeah,
是的
I mean,
我的意思是
I'm looking forward to seeing things like that being integrated the Vue CLI
我很期待看到 Vite 能融合到 Vue CLI 中。
because I like the opinion that you get with the CLI because I don't want...
我很喜欢你关于 CLI 的观点，
I spent a lot of time working through different frameworks and different projects that I have the context which quite a bit,
我花了很多时间研究不同的框架和不同的项目
especially in my role.
尤其是在我的角色里
I'd get home,
我回家
you know we just ship or on a random stuff and then move on to the next thing.
你知道的 我们只是随机地运送一些东西再转移到下一件东西上
I think it's like a dev raw thing really,
我觉得就开发原始的东西一样，
and I imagine folks you do like they do a lot of production sites in like agencies.
我想你们会喜欢的人他们会在代理机构做很多的制作网站
So my question is,
我的问题是
Is Vite
Vite
extendable and other different frameworks within the JavaScript ecosystem.
能否在 JavaScript 生态系统中的其他框架上扩展呢？
Yeah,
是的
yeah,
当然
so we have,
我们有
so There are several different ways to look at it.
有几种不同的方法来看待它
So first of all,
首先
Vite is framework agnostic,
Vite 与框架无关，
so you can use Vite to work with almost any like framework of choice.
因此，可以使用 Vite 来处理几乎任何框架。
And then Vite itself exposes a pretty pretty well defined JavaScript API so you can use Vite inside a higher level tool.
而且 Vite 提供了定义得非常好的 JavaScript API ，这样你就可以在更高级别的工具中使用 Vite 了.
So an example is VitePress,
一个例子是 VitePress，
which is a static site generator that is built on top of Vite.
是基于 Vite 的静态的网站生成器。
It actually wraps Vite internally and does a bunch of opinioned Vite stuff on top of it,
VitePress 在内部使用 Vite 并添加了一系列约定配置。
which I can probably show around,
我可以带你看看。
show it a bit.
稍微看一下
Do you have something to prepare?
你有准备好的吗？
Not really,
其实没有
but if so,
但如果是样
it is pretty cool because it doesn't really need like I really like this life seemed that I can just show how it works instead of talking about it.
很酷，因为我更像演示它如何工作的，而不是仅仅谈论它。
Actually,
实际上
yeah,
是的
I personally,
我个人
I,
我
we talked about this before were alive,
我们之前谈过，我们在直播，
but I wanted to have the fact. And I know a lot of folks are downstream haven't been here before on Open Source Friday,
但我知道的是，很多观众都是第一次来到 Open Souce Friday.
but it's an opportunity for us to have conversations about projects.
我们在这里谈论开源项目，
Open up the web browser and talk as opposed to like a podcast where you get a lot of high level and sort of walk through different patterns without getting they'll actually show it.
打开浏览器，和播客不同，在播客里你会得到很多高水平的内容，通过不同的模式，但是不会像这样实时的展示，
And then I'm going to have any bill read the show notes. But it's nice to see is just give us the examples this right here and right in front of us.
我们会看演示稿，但是能在面前看到真实的例子实在是太好了。
So I'm going to just like quickly good Tailwind going because so this is just installing a bunch of stuff,
好的，我要快速地过一下 Tailwind， 因为这里只是安装了一些依赖。
so I'm going to use yarn add
我要用 yarn add
-D with all these Tailwind stuff,
-D 和所有这些 Tailwind 相关的包
so these are just like standard dependencies that Tailwind wants you to install.
这些就是 Tailwind 需要你安装的标准的依赖。
Once you install that,
安装好之后
I'm going to tailwind.
输入 tailwind
There's that tailwindcss init -P.
tailwindcss init -P
So if you're wondering why I was able to run that without the npx prefix because I configured my path to include the the node_modules in the current directory.
如果你想知道为我为什么能够在没用 npx 前缀的情况下运行它，因为我将当前路径的 node_modules 配置到了环境变量中。
So I can always run the basing in the current node_modules in the current directory without any prefix.
因此，我总是可以不带前缀调用 node_modules 里面的命令
Ok.
好的
That's this your personal development to its environment.
这是你自己配置的开发环境。
Yeah,
是的
that's just a thing that I do.
是我常做的事
Okay,
好吧
I mean,
我的意思是
I love the other thing I love about this is I get to learn from other people who were at how to write code to think I'm pair programming for you,
我喜欢这个节目的另一原因是，我可以从其他人那里学习如何写代码，感觉是在为你们编程
but I'm really this sort of in the passenger seat.
但我真的是坐在副驾驶座上
Watch a new code.
观看新代码
And yeah,
是的
I love this cool.
我喜欢种酷
Just a hands up
稍微说了一句
So I just created this tailwind config this postcss.config.js
我创建了 Tailwind 的配置，在 postcss.config.js 里
so there is really nothing special to do here.
里没有特别的事情要做
Other than this thing I mean,
除了一点，
this is kind of.
有点
Some of these specific so ignore this,
有些具体的配置，请忽略这些
because this is like a tailwind specific thing,
因为这是 tailwind 的特殊配置
but this is the source code you want to actually just copy and put it here.
但是你需要复制并放到里的源码
And just reenable this.
取消注释
And then OK,
好了
so pages actually already reloaded is so I think I should have tailwind CSS in there.
页面实际上已经重新加载了，我认为 tailwind css 应该已经加载了，
so I want to.
我想
I don't use tailwind css just like enough
我没怎么用过 tailwind css
I think something like class = 3xl
我觉得应该这么写： class = 3xl
No？
没生效吗？
no.
确实没有生效
Actually,
实际上
if anybody want to be a tailwind expert
如果有人想当 tailwind 专家，
if you want to drop whatever the,
如果你想放弃任何东西
oh,
哦
it's text dash.
需要加 text- 前缀
text-3xl
text-3xl
This is the anthoer thing that programming on Twitch
这也是一点，观众能看到我们在 Twitch 上在线编程。
Ah, so it doesn't really work wondering why it's not working.
啊，没有生效，我们来看看是什么原因。
Let's see.
让我们看看。
I don't know if you have a chat open,
我不知道你开没开聊天窗口，
but text-3xl
但 text-3xl...
Everybody is now searching the docks where you two as well.
所有人都在搜你看的文档，
Yeah,
是的
well,
好吧
it's not actually updating the index.html doesn't mean that all because I'm actually overriding should hear here.
实际上 index.html 没有更新， 哦， 原来在这里我把 h1 的样式给覆盖了啊！
so now text-3xl
现在 class 是 text-3xl 了
and still isn't really working so styled with CSS.
但是对应的 CSS 仍然没有生效，
So the cool thing about so another thing I want to show case here is when you are debugging with something like Vite.
里我想展示的另一件很酷的事是，你可以看到我现场调试 Vite,
because we don't concoct need everything.
因为我们不需要捏造一切
So the easiest way to debug stuff is just looking at the network tab.
最简单的调试方法是查看network选项卡
Vite's every module is actually a individual request here,
Vite 的每个模块都是单独的请求
so I'm just going to look at this and it's not really doing anything.
我们看 styel.css 文件，它什么也没做，
Yeah,
是的
I think this is because I didn't restart the server.
我想是因为我没有重启服务器。
is importing the tailwind library file?
没有导入 tailwind 库是吗
You go,
好了，
Ah,
啊
there are OK,
有好的
Something changed.
事情发生了变化
Yeah,
是的
so I restarted server because they didn't know the post css config previously, it cached.
我重启了服务器，因为之前缓存了，不知道 post css 的配置。
Before we start,
在我们开始之前
I added the postcss config,
我添加了 postcss 的配置，
and the server was like I didn't notice.
服务器说：我没注意到
it's already here,
它已经在里
It just goes to show that even Evan You needs to debug?
原来尤雨溪也需要调试啊
Sometimes I get this line of code on a whim.
有时我心血来潮就会写出行代码
Yeah,
是的
OK.
好的
And then looking at the index.html
再看看 index.html
we're not importing the tailwind CSS , ...we are, got it.
我们是不是没导入 tailwind CSS 的文件，哦，导入了，明白了。
we're using this link here,
我们用的是 link
got it so so it works,
样式生效了
as you can see.
如你所见
PostCSS also works over these normal links,
PostCSS 也可以通过些正常的链接引入。
because this is treated as a dependency in Vite land as well.
因为它在 Vite 中也被视为一种依赖，
So if you have like nested at imports inside the CSS file,
如果你在CSS文件中嵌套了 import ，
we also trace all of that.
我们也会追踪所有些
We also kind of record the module graph, the dependency chain,
我们也会记录模块图和依赖链路。
so you add it like nested at import CSS files.
你在 CSS 文件嵌套的 import 的文件，
We also do hot module replacement and all that.
我们也会热更新。
ah,
啊
OK,
好吧
so that's if I think we're going to wrap it up here for CSS
如果我认为我们可以结束 CSS 的部分了。
it's actually.
实际上，
Maybe also showcase something like
也许还可以展示一些东西，比如
I'm going to yarn add -D sass
yarn add -D sass
So I'm just installing sass itself and I'm going to create a new file called style.scss
我只安装了 sass，然后创建新文件，style.scss
Then color.
颜色
Red, is that the syntax?
红色，语法是这样的吗？
So I wrote some scss
我写过一些 scss
And I'm going to just link it like this.
我要像这样把它们链接起来
So,
所以
yeah,
是的
so you install says and then you can use sass or scss
安装了 sass 依赖，就可以用 sass 或 scss 了
and it just works like this.
它能够正常工作
Of course,
当然
you can also do it like this if you want.
如果你愿意，也可以像这样导入 scss 文件
Or it's the same way.
这两种是一样的。
Or you can do.
你也可以么做
Something like this.
是
Also works.
这样也可以。
so most of the commission of stuff that you expect that should work，it probably will work.
你所期望的大部分情况都能正常运行。
And this is because we didn't do anything here is I'm just going to change this to style.scss
这里没有生效是因为在 main.js 中没引入 style.scss，我们来引入它
And reloads the page.
页面重新加载了
And then real quick going back to the vite config
我们快速回到 vite 配置文件
We didn't do much to set this up.
我们没有做太多准备
We did create some post growth,
我们确实创造了一些后期增长
there was the config that we had before,
我们之前有个配置
so we didn't really do anything too.
那个配置没用
Yeah,
是的
this work,
项工作
we didn't really like ...
是的，
This is actually unnecessary , I know because I was just showing how you can customize CSS modules here.
我知道这些其实不是必要的 ，因为我刚刚展示了如何配置 CSS 模块
OK,
好吧
excellent,
优秀的
Yeah,
是的
so technically,
从技术上讲
like anything you don't need just like remove them,
就像任何你不需要的东西，就删掉它们
and it doesn't affect anything.
也不会影响你
if you just want sass like this is all you need to work with sass
你如果只需要 sass，这就是你需要做的事情。
So really like it's more like if you want to go the super super minimal route, like you just have your HTML CSS and JavaScript optionally with CSS or a preprocessor like this.
如果你想走非常非常小的路线，就像这里你只需要 HTML、CSS 和 Javascript 以及可选的 CSS 预处理器这些静态文件。
This is not much from a static file server except it magically knows some of the stuff that you want to use.
它除了可以神奇地知道一些你想用的东西之外和静态文件服务器没什么区别。
Okay,
好吧
So.
所以
So this is for people who want to just like have a you know, a smarter server,
这是给那些想要更聪明服务器的人的。
But we can do more than this obviously.
但很明显，我们可以做的远不止这些。
So one use case that I have and because they are doing so much to twitch streaming this year,
我这有一个例子，因为我们今年在 twitch 上做了很多直播。
and we've just had a live stream last week me and Michelle,
上周我和米歇尔刚刚进行了直播。
Michelle from Australia I was given,
来自澳大利亚的米歇尔
and then though I was making the distinction.
尽管我在做区分
But we build a twitch bot,
我们创建了一个 twitch 机器人
and then one thing I've noticed what things like OBS
我注意到的一件事是 OBS
so like right now we're leveraging obs to get everything on the screen at the moment.
我们现在是用 OBS 来将屏幕的画面展示出来的。
is that it has a JavaScript runtime and I've been messing around with using like Deno and js time inside of OBS,
它是有 JavaScript 运行时，我在使用 OBS 里面的 Deno 和 js time 时很混乱。
I haven't really published anything that works yet,
我还没有真正发布过任何有用的东西
but I'm curious of things like we talked about typescript,
但我比较好奇的是，我们讨论过了 typescript，
but what about things like Deno will that be compatible
但是像 Deno 的兼容性怎么样呢？
Deno Probably so,
Deno 是...
Deno is a whole different story because the signal is it's own thing.
Deno 则完全是另一回事，因为它自成体系。
So Vite is currently built on top of Node.js API
Vite 目前是基于 Node.js 的 API 的。
So that's not going to be travelled to get it running in Deno
所以不支持 Deno 。
OK,
好吧
that's good to know.
明白了。
All right,
看看接下来我们能做什么。
I'm going to add a dependency now,
我现在要添加依赖。
so let's say,
我们说
I want to use React.
我想用 React。
So I added react and react-dom inside main.js
我在 main.js 里加入了 react 和 react-dom。
We probably want to change this to jsx because we are going to use some JSX.
我们把 main.js 后缀改为 .jsx，因为我们要在这里使用 JSX语法。
So I'm going to say import React from react
import React from 'react';
ah.
啊
Import.
导入
import ReactDom from 'react-dom'
import ReactDom from 'react-dom'
I think that's how it works.
我想应该是这么写
So forgive me because I'm actually er ...
请原谅我，因为我 ...( React 不是很熟）
ReactDom.render
ReactDom.render
We all came to watch Evan You write React
我们都在围观尤雨溪写 React。
getElementById app,
getElementById app,
maybe.
也许是
So that means we need to have something here.
这意味着我们在这里需要加一些东西
So the main thing I would actually show casing here is not really like React
我这里要展示的并不是 React ...
but we need a App
但我们需要 App 组件
So function App.
So function App.
return h1 hello
return hello
So let's see.
让我们看看
No.
不
Of course,
当然
ah,
啊
because we change it to main.jsx so and kept a check to here.
因为我们把它改成了 main.jsx，这里改一下。
Alright,
好了
so you get hello on the web
hello 显示了
so this is rendered by React,
是 React 渲染的
and as you can see, jsx just kind of worked out of the box as well.
如你所见 JSX 也是开箱即用的。
You didn't need to configure anything.
你不需要任何配置。
it kind of just worked so same for if you use tsx.
如果你用 tsx 也是一样的。
And let's do that export function app like this.
我们这样导出 App
So remember,
记住
you need to react because we are using the we have sixteen transform.
你需要手动引入 React，因为我们还在用 React 16 版本。
And instead of that,
取而代之的是
I'm going to say imports  from './App'.
imports  from './App'
And it works the same way so.
它们也一样工作。
So typescript jsx tsx works out of the box.
所以 typescript , jsx, tsx 都是开箱即用的。
you can just import them and they just work.
你可以直接导入，它们就能正常工作。
Ah,
啊
you didn't even need to install typescript itself.
你甚至不需要安装typescript本身
The assumption here is you will likely be doing type check,
这里的假设是你要做类型检查。
And so when you're developing your IDE probably know something.
当你开发你的 IDE 能得知一些事情。
So you can add a ts config here and your IDE will start linting these ts files and give you errors and warnings.
你可以添加一个 ts 配置文件，然后 IDE 就可以 lint 你的文件，给到你错误和警告的提示。
So Vite itself doesn't care about any of the type checks.
Vite 本身并不关心任何类型检查。
All it does is transform the syntax into actual JavaScript that the browser can understand.
它所做的只是将语法转换为浏览器能够理解的 JavaScript。
Ah,
啊
and it does that using esbuild so this is where we start to
用 esbuild 就能做到，我们回到开始的地方
I should already leveraged esbuilding two places up to this point.
我用了 esbuild 两处位置。
The first is esbuild is transforming these jsx and tsx files into plain js for us.
第一处使用 esbuild 的地方是它帮我们把 tsx 和 jsx 转为普通的 js 文件。
So for those who don't know what esbuild is,
这里为不知道 esbuild 是什么的观众解释一下，
It's a javascript build tool transpile tool that's written in Go.
Esbuild 是用 Go 语言开发的 JavaScript 构建和转义工具。
So it's written it's compiled to native binaries.
它被编译成原始的二进制文件
And it's extremely extremely fast.
它非常非常快
And that was shipped pretty recently wasn't it ？
它是最近才出的吗？
It's actually been around for a while.
其实已经有一段时间了。
yeah,
是的
maybe it just made the newsletters recently
也许它最近才有一些新闻。
I mean,
我的意思是
it takes a time for these kinds of projects to mature because it's covering so much features but eh..
Esbuild 之类的项目需要一段时间才能成熟，因为它覆盖了太多的特性，但是...
But the basic idea here is.
但里的基本思想是
When you installed Vite were already installed esbuild for you,
当你安装 Vite 时就为你安装好了 esbuild。
so you don't. You don't need to install anything extra to get these translations,
你不需要安装任何额外工具来对这些文件进行转义。
and this is at least twenty to thirty times faster than vanilla tsc.
Esbuild 比传统的 tsc 至少快 20 到 30 倍。
So tsc you will probably take like thirty forty milliseconds to transpile tsx file,
TSC 会花 30-40 毫秒编译 tsx 文件。
But with esbuild it's like one millisecond most of the time.
但用 esbuild 编译一般只需要 1 毫秒。
And Vite leverage is that so imagine if you have a project like one hundred ts files,
Vite 就是利用了 esbuild 这一点，比如一个项目有上百个 ts 文件，
so that kind of add up.
这些加起来就会省很多时间。
Another aspect of this is when we started server here.
用到 esbuild 的另一方面是当我们在里启动 server 时。
notice this thing here,
注意这里
says new dependency found react and react-dom。
这里提示检测到新的依赖 react 和 react-dom。
If you are used to using React with like, create-react-app or webpack,
如果你之前用过 creat-react-app 或者 webpack 来开发 React 项目。
you kind of used to like doing like import React from react like this,
你习惯了这样写： import React from 'react'
and it just works,
它就能正常工作。
and sometimes we may even do things like you know,
有时我们甚至会这样做：
named exports like this,
像这样命名的导出
but if you actually look at what the files React is shipping.
但如果你真的去查看 React 到底传递了什么文件。
Let's going to React here and look at the package.json here.
我们打开 react 文件夹，查看里面的 package.json 文件。
it says main: index.js
里面写着入口文件是 index.js
so index.js it says module.exports equals require blah, blah blah.
在 index.js 里有 module.exports = require 一些东西
And this is actually CommonJS.
这其实是 CommonJS。
So React doesn't ship native es modules, it ships CommonJS.
React 没有导出原生的 ES 模块，它导出的是 CommonJS 。
Ships CommonJS,
导出 CommonJS
but we are able to just imported like an actual es module here,
但是我们可以像 ES 模块一样引入进来。
so there is obviously something going on in the background.
很明显在背后中发生了一些事情。
Eh, webpack, Rollup you know, if you use this with Rollup
像 webpack、Rollup 都是如此，如果你使用的是 Rollup
you will need something like rollup-plugin-commonjs.
你需要 rollup-plugin-commonjs 这个插件
Webpack does a lot of the interrupt behind the behind the scene.
同样 webpack 也在后面做了很多处理。
But how do we get to make React actually working the browser?
但如何让 React 在浏览器中运行呢
So let's take a look at the network here.
让我们来看看 Network 标签
Ah,
啊
ah,
上帝
God,
我如何
I can't get to grab this part anyway.
反正我也找不到这块..
So here's the React
哦，React 在这里。
Notice that we are getting this require_react,
注意这里的 require_react 。
so this all of this code is actually generated by esbuild
些代码都是 esbuild 生成的。
So.
所以
When we restart the server,
当我们重启服务器时
if I say.
如果我说
vite --force.
vite --force.
There is a thing here,
这里有 ...
What's the force command.
Force 命令是什么意思？
The force means.
Force 意思是
Ignore the dependency cache reforce process all the dependencies.
忽略依赖的缓存，重新处理全部的依赖。
OK, intresting
好吧，有意思。
yeah,
是的
so if you don't,
如果你不样做
it won't.
它不会
It will check some hash,
它会检查一些哈希
and if the hash matches,
如果哈希匹配
you won't need to do anything when you restart the server.
重新启动服务器时，它不会做任何事情。
But if you've passed a force it will
但如果你传递了 force 命令，
You just didn't pass the force.
你只是没有传 force
So it will detect it.
它会检测到它
So what Vite is doing here is,
Vite 在里的作用是
it will look at your source code,
它会查看你的源码，
notice you are relying on react and react-dom.
注意，你的依赖是 react 和 react-dom。
And then it will check react and react-dom and notice they are not actually es modules.
然后 Vite 会检查 react 和 react-dom 发现它们并不是 ES 模块。
which means we need to do something about them,
也说我们得对他们做点什么。
So we will use esbuild to process them prebundle them into something that actually works in the browser as native es modules.
所以，我们使用 esbuild 来处理它们，将它们预打包，使他们能够在浏览器中作为原生 ES 模块工作。
And we have some also smart interrupts so that you can use named exports,
我们还有一些智能拦截，以便你可以使用命名导出。
even though technically,
尽管从技术上讲
A CommonJS module transform to es module only has a single default export,
CommonJS 转换为 ES 模块只有默认的 export。
But we kind of make that work with some some runtime interrupt,
但我们用一些运行时中断能够让它工作。
And the benefit of this is kind of twofold.
这样做的好处有两点。
The first is you make CommonJS modules work as native ES modules.
第一点是将 CommonJS 模块作为原生的 ES 模块运行。
Another benefit of this is say you have something like lodash-es.
另外一点好处是，比如你使用了像 lodash-es 这样的包。
Lodash-es has like six hundred internal modules.
它内部有 600 多个模块。
When you import lodash-es
当你导入 lodash-es 时，
Without any optimization,
如果没有任何优化，
you are loading all those six six hundred modules here.
浏览器会加载全部 600 多个模块，
So,
所以
if you look at the network tab when you load.
如果你在加载时查看 network 选项卡，
Maybe I can just do that in yarn add lodash-es
我们来添加 lodash-es 依赖
And I'm going to say import _ from 'lodash-es'
这里写 import _ from 'lodash-es'
Well,
好吧
that didn't actually resulting in a lot of request because our server,
这里并没有很多请求，这是因为我们的服务器，
the Vite servers smartly detect a lodash-es and chunked into a single file on the fly.
Vite 服务器智能检测到 lodash-es，并快速将其打包成一个文件。
So if we didn't do that,
如果我们不这样做，
you'll this will you will see like six hundred requests here and it's going to jam the browser,
你会看到这里有 600 多个请求，这会阻塞浏览器，
even though it's relatively fast,
尽管它相对较快
it's like there are still a lot of overhead when you process an http request.
但是在处理 Http 请求时，仍然会有很多开销。
so ideally,
理想情况下
even during dev,
即使在 dev 环境
we still want to reduce number requests.
我们仍然希望减少请求的数量
but we'd kind of does this for you so that even if you import a dependency with even a thousand internal modules,
但我们会帮你做了这件事，即使你的依赖内部有上千个模块。
we still kind of chunk it into a single file here and because we do that with esbuild.
我们还是会用 esbuild 把它们打包成一个文件。
It's so fast like how much time it did.
它是如此的快。
This within like a second less than a second.
不到一秒
But if you do,
但如果你样做了
this would say something.
说明了一些问题
so this comes into play like,
就产生了
because even were huge dependencies may be like.
因为即使是体积巨大的依赖也是一样快速。
There are yarn add @material-ui/core.
我们键入 yarn add @material-ui/core.
So this is going to be pretty intense, right.
这里将会非常大。
import m from '@material-ui/core'.
import m from '@material-ui/core'.
So we finish that we imported material-ui/core.
我们引入了 material-ui/core。
Ah,
啊
and still it takes less than a second.
但只需要不到一秒的时间
Granted.
理所当然
This is I'm running on an M1 ARM Mac which is insanely fast but still like this same thing.
这是在我的 M1 ARM 架构的 Mac 上运行的，它非常快。
If you process,
如果你处理这些，
it will say webpack or a Rollup, you probably have to wait a few seconds.
使用 wepack 或者 rollup，一般都需要等待几秒钟。
And so this so this is where esbuild really makes this process just like insanely fast
对于速度这块我测试过一个项目。
And some of the noticeable differences like I've test.
使用不同工具速度有明显差异。
This is tested this on a real world app using React and material-ui and a bunch of other dependencies.
这是一个基于 React 和 material-ui 还有其他依赖的真实项目。
And I try to pre bundle with Rollup and took me twenty eight seconds on M1 Mac.
我尝试使用 rollup 在我的 M1 Mac 上打包，花了 28 秒钟。
And we've got a curiosity are you on M1 mac right now
你现在用的就是 M1 Mac 吗？
Yes,
是的
I am here.
我在里
Yeah,
你刚才说的那些话
So after we switched Vite to use esbuild for this process,
是的
it took one point five seconds.
它只花了 1.5 秒。
so that's like twenty times faster startup time,
启动时间就快了 20 倍。
and because every time you detect a new import,
因为每次你检测到新的导入，
or you add new dependencies,
或者添加新的依赖项
the cache will likely invalidates.
缓存会失效，
So you kind of have to do this relatively frequently.
所以预打包要经常做，
So having esbuild handle this is just like a lifesaver because just like cut down the time so much.
因此用 esbuild 来处理这些简直是救命稻草， 因为样可以节省很多时间。
Most of the time.
大多数时候
With with M1 plus esbuild
用 M1 芯片和 esbuild，
I'm just,
我只是
I'll start getting patient whenever I start a project and I have to wait more than one second.
如果启动项目必须等待超过一秒钟，我就会失去耐心。
You're any kind of.
你是任何一种
Yeah,
是的
I'm spoiled honestly.
说实话，我是被宠坏了。
And also note esbuild is currently still only ships Intel binary.
还需要注意的是 esbuild 目前是基于 Intel 的发布版本。
It doesn't have an apple silicon native binary of esbuild yet.
它还没有支持原生苹果芯片的二进制版本。
I think the latest version of Go does support it.
我认为最新版本 Go 已经支持了。
But esbuild it hasn't really started shipping the ARM native binaries.
但是 esbuild 还没有发布其支持 ARM 架构的二进制版本。
Yet so we are actually running esbuild on M1 Mac back through Rosetta 2.
我们实际上是通过 Rosetta 2 运行的 esbuild.
so imagine it can be another like twenty to thirty percent faster.
想象一下，它可以再快 20% 到 30%，
once we have native ARM Mac esbuild binaries.
一旦我们有了支持 Mac ARM 架构的 esbuild。
So,
所以
yeah,
是的
so this is part of where the Vite the fastness comes into play when you,
这也是 vite 快速的一部分。
when you notice the difference when you have not just for a simple demo project,
当你注意到不同之，当你不仅仅是为了简单的演示项目
when you have a real project with like hundreds of dependencies,
当你项目有上百个依赖的项目时
this is start to be a very, very significant It's very, very significant difference in terms of the DX, right.
在体验上是有很大不同的。
So if you have to wait like half a minute or a whole minute before every time you spin up the dev server or I'm going to be really reluctant to even think about working on the project.
如果每次你都要等上半分钟或者一分钟，我就很不想做这个项目了。
All right.
是的。
And this kind of helps me with debugging tool,
这也有助于我调试，
because now,
因为现在
like every time someone reports a new thing,
就像每次有人向我反馈新的问题，
I clone the reproduction.
我把仓库 clone 下来，
It almost always starts instantly.
然后几乎是马上就能启动了。
I don't have to like wait.
我不需要等
So it just makes debugging Vite itself also much more pleasant.
因此，调试 Vite 本身也变得更加令人愉快。
Yeah,
是的
I mean,
我的意思是
I've got some projects that do actually could be debugging a lot of my regular site actually takes quite some time for you to build,
我有一些需要调试的项目，我的很多常规网站实际上需要你花很多时间来启动。
so I won't drop any frameworks any names down,
我不会想删除任何框架
but it's got some issues.
但它也有一些问题。
I do have little questions from the chat there.
在聊天室有一些问题。
What about our production and is Vite ready for production?
我们的生产情况怎么样，vite 可以用在生产环境吗？
I know there's a beta flag on the 2.0 right now on the repo.
我知道现在 vite 仓库里有一个 flag 是 2.0 的 beta 版本。
So we are actually pretty stable for the past few weeks on no major bugs left really.
在过去的几周我们已经开始稳定下来了，没有特别大的缺陷遗留。
So there are a few small edge cases if you have some particularly tricky dependencies where it's like a mix of ES modules in CommonJS,
如果你有一些特别棘手的依赖关系，那么还有一些小的边缘情况：比如 CommonJS 中混合了 ES 模块。
there may be small issues,
会有一些小问题
but for the most parts we already have close to thirty thousand downloads per week and.
但大多数情况下没问题，我们每周有接近三万多的下载量。
The latest few versions has been pretty stable,
最新几个版本相当稳定。
so I think we are going out of beta pretty soon.
我认为我们很快就会推出正式版。
One thing I kind of want to talk about is the production story is like when you want to shift to production.
我们接着来看生产模式。如果你想转向生产，
Let's add a script here.
让我们在这里添加脚本。
build: 'vite build'
build: 'vite build'
So that is literally it.
这就是字面上的意思
you just run yarn build so anything that's you can have working in dev
你执行 yarn run build。你在 dev 环境能够正常运行的话，
Theoretically,
从理论上讲
we guarantee that we guarantee that it will work in build as well.
我们保证我们保证它在生产环境也能运行。
So if it doesn't work as expected,
如果不符合预期，
then it's a bug.
那么这就是漏洞了，
we'll fix it.
我们会解决它
But the idea is anything that.
但基本的想法是，
So we built it,
我们建造了它
and we also give you a Vite command called.
我们也有一个 Vite 命令：
vite preview.
vite preview
Which we'll just serve this directory that we just build,
这会启动服务器，运行我们刚打包创建的文件。
which is the dist directory and it'll surveyed in production.
也就是 dist 目录，它会运行生产包。
So this is the production bill.
这是生产版本。
We do a lot of interesting stuff in production for the production build,
我们在生产环节上做了很多有趣的事情
and so in the features section in our docs here.
在我们文档的 Feature 部分，
There is a dedicated section here says Build Optimizations.
里面有专门的构建优化章节，
The native target.
构建目标
The default target build target for vite is browsers that support native es modules.
Vite 默认的构建目标是支持原生 ES 模块的浏览器。
So by default it doesn't support IE 11.
默认情况下，它不支持 IE 11。
So this is something to keep in mind.
这点需要注意。
Vite is modern by defaults,
Vite 默认支持现代浏览器。
but we do have opt in support for legacy browsers.
但是我们也有支持旧浏览器的选项。
Which I'll talk about in a bit.
我一会儿会讲到。
But if you're targeting modern only obviously you don't need to do expensive babel, babel preset m transformations which makes the build faster as well.
但如果你的目标是现代浏览器。显然你不需要做非常耗时的 Babel 预设转义，这样会更快。
We automatically polyfill dynamic import so that it works.
我们自动 polyfill 了动态导入功能。
There is actually a support discrepancy between native es modules and native es modules dynamic import.
实际上，原生的 ES 模块和原生的 ES 动态导入模块有支持差异。
So we polyfill that's you just make it.
我们将其 polyfill 了。
Even we have CSS code splitting.
我们还有 CSS 代码分割。
So if you, all the code splitting in a vite project can be done with just es module dynamic import.
在 vite 项目中，所有的代码分割都可以通过动态 ES 模块导入来解决。
We,
我们
because we treat CSS is part of the module graph as well.
因为我们将 CSS 也视为模块图的一部分。
We can code split CSS.
我们可以对 CSS 做代码分割。
So if you have async chunk,
如果是异步的包，
a lazy route
懒加载的路由，
all the CSS import by that route is split into a separate file and we also when you win,
所有被懒加载路由导入的 CSS 都被分割成单独的文件。
that chunk is being requested.
当这个包被请求时，
We fetch the Javascript and CSS in parallel.
我们并行地获取 JavaScript 和 CSS 文件。
Yeah,
是的
then ensure the CSS is loaded before the JavaScript module is evaluated.
确保 JavaScript 模块被解析之前完成 CSS 加载。
so you don't get the Flash of unstyled content
这样就不会出现"无样式内容闪烁"（FOUC）的问题了。
So this is all done for you out of the box,
这些功能都是开箱即用的。
you don't need to configure anything if you want to get the same working with webpack
你不需要配置任何东西。如果用 webpack 实现相同功能，
it's another story,
那就是另一段故事了。
like you have to look into CSS
你需要查看 CSS，
Many CSS is strapped logging.
很多 CSS 是带日志的。
All the stuff that question has come up quite a few times,
有个问题已经提过很多次了
and I wasn't sure if it was relevant,
我不确定是否相关
but server side rendering, we agreed that vite does this,
Vite 支持 SSR 吗？
I can imagine server side rendering being a really good story for vite.
我想讲讲 Vite 的服务端渲染比较好。
So vite has currently experimental server side rendering.
嗯，Vite 的 SSR 目前是实验性的。
Ah,
啊
so yes,
是的
I can know.
我可以知道
Setting up in from scratch can be a bit involved because of because the idea here is,
从零开始设置有点复杂，这里的思想是，
but the idea here so.
但是这里的思想是
Let's take a step back and think about what service surrendering what we need with a bundler to get services rendering to work.
让我们退后一步，我们需要 SSR 做什么，我们需要打包工具打出的代码能够运行在服务端。
The idea is,
我们的想法是
you want your code to be running in GitHub as well,
你想让你的代码在 nodejs 里运行
but we are writing.
但我们正在写
We're writing code.
我们编写代码
Thus using ESM
但是我们使用了 ES 模块
If you are not using like the latest version of node module,
如果你使用的不是 nodejs 的最新版本，
latest version of GitHub with native es module support,
nodejs 的最新版本支持原生 ES 模块。
this code won't run right because previous versions of GitHub exports CommonJS.
这段代码不能正常运行，因为以前的 nodejs 版本需要 CommonJS。
And what we are doing here is we provide a programmatic API called ssrLoadModule.
而我们在里所做的是提供可编程 API ssrLoadModule。
So this is inspired by some of the work that Rich Harris is doing in Svelte and the idea is
我们受到了里奇·哈里斯在 Svelte 工作的想法的启发。
You can use vite as a middleware inside an existing GitHub server,
可以在现有的 nodejs 服务器中使用 vite 作为中间件。
so if you are doing so,
如果你这么做，
surrendering you likely want to control the server yourself right so you can use,
你想自己控制服务器，这样你就可以，
say I express server run vite as a middleware inside of it.
比如 express 服务器运行 vite 作为它内部的中间件。
And then use this method called vite.ssrLoadModule.
使用称 vite.ssrLoadModule 来加载我们的模块。
And load it your server load your server entry like this.
像这样加载 entry-server.js 文件。
That's pretty much it.
差不多了。
your server entry runs in GitHub and it can use the same es import syntax to load the rest of your application.
你的服务器入口在 nodejs 中运行，它可以使用相同的 ES 模块导入语法来加载应用的剩余部分。
Obviously you need to make sure you write your code that is node compatible,
显然你需要确保你的代码是兼容 nodejs 的。
but you can use es module syntax and vite will transform these syntax on the fly into something that's compatible to CommonJS
但是你可以使用 ES 模型语法，而 vite 会动态地把些语法快速转换成兼容 CommonJS 的语法。
so it can run in GitHub
这样它就能真正运行在 nodejs 环境了。
And what we typically do in a webpack,
我们通常在 webpack 里的做法是，
based as the source setup is,
根据源程序设置
we actually do a whole ssr bundle as you develop,
我们在开发过程将应用全部打包，
so it uses webpack to bundle your whole application and output it as CommonJS so that it runs in GitHub.
因此 它使用webpack将您的整个应用程序打包，并将其作为 CommonJS 导出，以便在 nodejs 环境中运行。
The downside of this is obviously every time you edit a file,
但是这样缺点很明显，每次当你编辑文件时，
you are be bundling the whole application for a CommonJS.
你要把整个应用打包
and that is slow with vite when you load this are these modules are similarly cached individually,
这样会很慢。当你用 vite 时，这些模块都是单独缓存的。
like just like in the browser right?
就像在浏览器里，对吧
One of the reasons we want you to leverage native ESM is because each module is now cached individually.
我们利用原生 ES 模块的原因之一是每个模型都能够单独缓存。
so we do hot module replacement,
我们做模块热更新，
where only invalidating the specific modules that's being edited.
在这里只会使正在编辑的模型失效，
Similarly,
同样的
for the service are rendering story,
对于服务端渲染也一样。
we cache all these modules that's specifically instantiated for ssr in our internal module graph,
我们为 ssr 实例化缓存所模块为，使用在内部模块图中。
and when you edit a file,
当你编辑文件时
we only invalidate the certain modules that's affected by this specific edit.
我们只会将正在编辑的模块失效。
so you can kind of think of it as hot module replacement for service side rendering during development,
你可以把它看作是开发时的 SSR 模块热更新。
so you never rebundle your whole app.
不需要整体重新打包。
Also vite will smartly externalize dependencies that ships CommonJS.
另外 Vite 也会智能识别 CommonJS 的模块。
for example,
例如
if you use Vue or React, right, React is already CommonJS
如果你用 Vue 或者 React，比如你用 React，React 已经是 CommonJS 了
So if you use,
如果你用
React in server side rendering.
React 在 SSR 中。
you just required,
你只需要 require，
you don't want to say like bundle it process it that's unnecessary because React shifts as CommonJS so that vite will detect all of these dependencies automatically externalize them,
不需要打包编译，因为没有必要， React 已经是 CommonJS 了，vite 检测全部依赖，并自动外部化它们。
and when you import React
当你使用 import React 时，
it's actually just calling.
它实际上只是在调用
require react under the hood so you don't pay the cost of.
require react ，这样你就不用付出额外的打包编译成本。
Like processing react as part of a bundle,
就像处理 React 作为包的一部分一样
every change in a lot of this is done automatically,
每改变都是自动完成的
and we have this guide further server side rendering.
这里有关于 SSR 的进一步指引。
If you go to our github repo.
如果你去我们的 GitHub 仓库，
we also have actually,
实际上，我们还有
I can probably shoot here.
我可以在里。。。
So what you were just explaining does that also fall in line with the context of incremental builds
你刚才解释的和增量构建是类似的吗？
It's different from incremental builds,
它与增量构建不同
so builds are still full because incremental builds are a lot more difficult.
增量构建仍然是全的，因为增量构建要困难得多
This is mostly focused on the development experience,
我们刚才说的主要集中在开发体验上
like when you're developing.
比如你在开发的时候。
Okay,
好吧
Gotcha,
明白了
Yeah,
是的
and quick time check,
我们看一下时间。
I'd know we only book this time for an hour,
我们只预约了 1 个小时。
but okay,
但是好吧
I'm good to keep going if you want to keep going,
如果你想继续，我们可以继续
if you want to finish some your thoughts.
如果你想把想法都讲完。
it seems like the chat is really love in this so far are getting the sort of hands on experience and looking over your shoulder.
到目前为止我们都收获了很多。
so,
所以
yeah,
是的
so if you're interested in server side rendering.
如果你对 SSR 感兴趣。
check out the github repos,
来看我们的 GitHub 仓库。
so we have this pretty comprehensive playground directory in the source code,
我们在源码中有非常全面的 playground 目录。
where it has these demo playground of all the major features.
它有所有主要功能的演示环境。
and these are two fully working server side rendering examples with Vue and React.
是两个完全有效的 SSR 例子，分别是 Vue 和 React 的。
So if you want to try them out,
如果你想尝试一下
just use these as references.
可以用这些作为参考
Cool.
很好。
OK,
好吧
so of all this idea,
在所有些想法中
there's one thing I still haven't really mentioned up to this point at which is hot module replacement.
到目前为止，模块热更新我还没有讲到。
so.
所以
I'm going to just create a new one to say cva is my local alias for create vite app.
我来新建一个项目，cvs 是 create-vite-app 的本地别名。
Ah.
啊
Each vite demo so I recreate,
每个 demo 我重新创建，
so when you run npm init add vitejs slash app.
使用 vite init
This is also what you'll see so it will run.
也是你看到的这样，它会运行。
The vitejs create app application on the fly,
vite 已经快速创建了应用。
and you can pick some of these existing templates that you can go with.
你可以从这些现有模板中选择需要的模板。
I say I'm going to just go with the basic Vue template here.
我这里选择基础的 Vue 模板。
vite view demo.
进到 vite-vue-demo 文件夹。
I'm going to just use my locally links.
我只使用本地链接
vite
提要
install the dependencies.
安装的依赖。
And I get so.
我得到了
This is.
是
Vue three app that's running on vite.
在 Vite 上运行的 Vue 3 应用。
Let me open this in code.
我用 VS Code 打开它。
So this is very standard if you worked with Vue CLI before,
如果你以前用过 Vue CLI，你会发现生成的文件结构很相似。
this will feel right at home right almost of the stuff is the same.
感觉和 Vue CLI 生成的一样。
So I obviously if I edit something,
很明显，如果我编辑一些东西
I'm going to.
我要去
Hit the counter.
点击计数器
Just to show that if the HTML doesn't actually glowed a stayed away.
只是为了说明 HTML 实际上没有闪烁。
An html is really,
Html 真的是
really fast,
非常快
so the idea here is,
这里的想法是
if you're working on a large application,
如果你正在开发大型应用程序
reloading the page on every edit is obviously not optimal,
每次编辑都重新加载页面显然不是最优的
especially say you have some page state where you're like.
特别是你有一些页面状态
I'm want to see how this dropdown look like when I'm tweaking the logic or tweaking the style,
我想看看下拉菜单或者调整样式和逻辑的时候。
you want to have the whole application reload and then you have to reopen the drop down every time.
如果重新加载整个应用，那每次都需要重新打开下拉列表
So hot module replacement is one thing.
模块热更新就不是这样了。
I believe that sort of eh,
我相信是那种，
If the couples,
如果
the feedback speed from the size of the application,
应用大小与反馈速度有关。
which is again like the this whole idea of making things faster,
就像让事情变得更快的想法
is because personally as it as a developer myself,
因为就我个人而言，作为开发者
whenever I'm working on something,
每当我在工作的时候
if I know something is going to take a long time,
如果我知道件事需要很长时间
I will be reluctant to do it.
我不愿意做件事
It just creates this friction just makes you less likely to do something it makes.
他会降低你工作的热情。
It makes you enjoy your work less.
会让你更不喜欢你的工作
so if everything is snappy and fast yours,
如果一切都很快，
you're a happier Developer and happier developers are more productive developers. That's what I believe so and how to make developers happy, make their tools fast.
那么你会更开心，更有效率。 我认为想让开发者更开心，就让他们使用的工具更快一些吧。
So that's the whole premise right so here,
这就是整个前提
if we take a higher level,
如果我们从更高的层面来看
look at would vite is trying to do here.
看看 vite 在这里要做的事情。
Why don't we just use esbuild for everything.
为不直接用 esbuild 来处理全部呢？
If it's so fast,
如果它么快
the thing is,
事情是
even if esbuilt is really fast.
即使 esbuild 非常快
you probably don't want to rebundle or your whole thing on every single edit,
你肯定不希望在每一次编辑时都重新打包全部内容
because even it's fast.
因为即使它是快速的
If it's going to get slower slower, the size of application grows.
它会随着应用大小的增长变得越来越慢。
The idea is,
我们的想法是
I want you to decouple the added feedback from the total size,
我想让你把增加的反馈和总规模结合起来
your application,
你的应用
which is why we need hot module replacement.
为什么我们需要模块热更新，
But the downside the challenge that we have had in the past is like say,
但我们过去遇到的挑战是，
with webpack
使用 webpack 的时候，
I don't know why.
我不知道为什么
But in practice,
但在实践中
we've noticed that webpack's hot module replacement performance just degrades as the size of the application grows.
我们已经注意到 webpack 的模块热更新性能随着应用大小增长极速下降。
Technically,
从技术上讲
I mean theoretically it shouldn't,
我的意思是理论上它不应该这样。
but that's what's happening and say in a large way,
但在很大程度上这就是正在发生的事情。
webpack application you,
使用 webpack 的应用
even with hot module replacement is not uncommon to wait a few seconds before it. The thing actually finally updates.
即使是用了模块热更新，通常需要等待几秒页面才会最终会更新。
but the premise of vite or other native ESM hot module replacement over native ESM.
但 vite 利用了原生的 ES 模块来做模块热更新。
so the premise is because each module is now cached individually.
前提是现在每个模块都是单独缓存的
When you edit a file,
当你编辑文件时
we simply invalidate the cache for their specific module and maybe a chain,
我们只需为它们特定的模块和链使其缓存无效。
an import chain up to all the way where we can say this is this is a reload boundary where we can reimport the module from here.
一条导入链可以重新引入模块。
So say,
说
when you are editing a Vue file,
当你编辑一些 Vue 文件时
the only thing that's being invalidated.
这个文件是唯一失效的。
It is this.
它是
Is this file itself.
是该文件本身。
so we're not doing any of the actual work saying like now let's recreated the whole bundle,
我们并没有将整个应用重新构建。
so that then we reload the page right.
这样我们就可以重新载入页面了
There's nothing like,
没有比
then all we're doing and say
我们就会看到
In fact,
事实上
if we look at the network tab here.
如果我们看一下network选项卡
God,
上帝
this is too.
是也
Can I clear no not this one,
我可以清除吗，不
this one anyway,
这一个
so uncharted territory for me.
对我来说是未知的领域
I've never seen such an active network tab.
我从未见过如此活跃的网络标签
Yes,
是的
all right,
好吧
I think the cool thing is like everything is imported individually,
我觉得很酷的一点是所有的东西都是单独导入的
and so here.
在这里
ah,
啊
OK,
好吧
this one.
这一个
So this is the only new network request that we made every time we adults,
这是我们每次编辑后生成的唯一一个新的请求。
we're just fetching an updated version of this specific file,
我们只是取回特定文件的更新版本
and then we apply the updates precisely so we don't reload the whole application.
我们精确地应用更新，这样就不会重新加载整个应用。
We don't need to do any bundling work and it just
我们不需要做任何打包的工作。
It's as precise as it can be.
它已经非常精确了。
As you mentioned things like tree shaking.
就像你提到的 tree shaking。
Vite, does it grab stuff that's not being used or actively being leveraged.
Vite 会将不使用的代码拿掉吗？
Tree shaking is a more like a production concern because our enduring development you do you don't really worry about loading a few extra kilobytes of.
Tree shaking 更多是生产环境使用的，我们在开发环境不用担心请求额外的几 KB。
In production,
在生产中
you do want to the leverage tree-shaking
你需要使用 tree shaking。
but that's kind of what the bunglers do I so for production vite still uses bundlers.
这是打包器做的事情，vite 也使用了打包器。
Vite is built on top of Rollup for production and,
Vite 的打包器是基于 Rollup 的。
in fact,
事实上
Vite plugins are a super set of Rollup plugins.
Vite 的插件是 Rollup 插件的超集。
So if you know how to write a Rollup plugin,
如果你知道如何写 Rollup 插件，
you already kind of know how to write a vite plugin.
那么你就会写 Vite 插件了。
A lot of the concepts like resolve id, transform load.
Vite 的很多概念，如 resolveid，transform load
There are exactly the same features,
都和 Rollup 一样。
extends Rollup's interface to provide a few of vite specific.
Vite 扩展了 Rollup 接口，并提供了几个
Vite specific properties or hooks,
Vite 专属的属性和钩子。
so to make it easier.
为了更简单
So I think that's that's pretty much said,
我想讲的差不多了
I don't know if there's anything I can.
我不知道这是否能够帮助到大家。
I want to talk about what we already talk about like built in frameworks support.
我想谈谈我们已经讨论过内置的框架支持。
I know there are a bunch of spelt users working on a svelte integration for vite as well.
我知道有一群用户在研究 vite 和 svelte 的整合。
In fact.
事实上
I know a fork of Rollup plugin felt just work pretty much just works in vite.
我发现一个 rollup 插件很有用，就 fork 它用在 vite 上。
There's a question that came up about just a point I just mentioned about Rollup
刚才有观众提到了 Rollup 的问题。
And why not use esbuild for production.
为什么不在生产环境也用 esbuild 呢？
So the thing here is esbuild for production still has a bunch of things.
Esbuild 用在生产环境还存在一些问题。
so esbuild story for bundling an application is still a little bit incomplete.
基本上 esbuild 对打包功能的支持不够完整。
I will say,
我想说
I think in a feature in the future.
我想在未来
where esbuild gets more robust application oriented bundling support.
当 esbuild 的打包功能更稳定
We'll probably you know it's a.
我们知道是
It's an open possibility that we can switch to it because we already leverage in the lot.
那么我们就会使用它，毕竟我们一直在使用它。
The thing here is,
问题是
for example,
例如
you want to have more control over the chunk rendering
你想对数据包渲染有更多的控制
and the into cross import the hash and handling assets, emitting files and then getting the bundle,
在生成哈希值，处理附件，提交文件等问题上
analyzing the bundle optimizing the cross imports.
对打包内容进行分析优化
and all that stuff with esbuild that sort of you know you pretty much.
所有这些你熟悉的东西，
You probable don't get any control over the chunking processing in esbuild right now.
现在都没法使用 esbuild 来处理。
So that's something.
目前是这样。
and I know.
我知道
Aaron Wallis said he is planning to rewrite code splitting in esbuild at some point.
亚伦·沃利斯说他计划写 eabuild 处理代码分割。
So which is why we don't really rely on it.
我们不依赖它的原因
I mean,
我的意思是
in terms of bundling for applique, bundling applications,
在打包应用层面，
Rollup is still a much more.
Rollup 还是更合适的。
I mean,
我的意思是
Battle test in a more robust choice at this point of time.
我们选择打包更稳定的 Rollup。
so obviously it means the production build of vite is going to be much slower than something that you know you.
很明显，不使用 esbuild 打包也意味着打包要慢很多
leverage esbuild all the way through,
我们一直用 esbuild 就很快。
but the benefit is you get you likely get a more robust and more efficient bundle for production,
但好处是你会得到更健壮更高效的生产包。
so one thing you can do is you can use esbuild as the minifier.
你可以做的一件事是你可以用 esbuild 来压缩文件。
So the default minifier is terser,
默认压缩器使用的是 terser。
but you can say vite build -- minify esbuild
但是你可以这样 vite build -- minify esbuild
ah,
啊
so we can use esbuild as the minifier which already speeds up the build by quite a bit,
我们可以用 esbuild 作为压缩器，这样会大大加快构建的速度。
but in most cases the bundle will be slightly larger.
但在大多数情况下，包会稍微大一些
So it's a tradeoff that you can make them.
你需要做出权衡。
Make your call yourself.
想一想
Are you willing to trade?
你愿意交换吗
Maybe five to ten percent larger bundle in return for faster builds.
也许大百分之五到十的额外大小来换取更快的打包速度。
It's up to you.
由你决定
OK,
好吧
excellent,
优秀的
yeah,
是的
and I think the last question would be how could folks stay up to date with vite checkout releases?
我想最后问题是人们如何跟上 vite 的进度。
And are you taking contributions right now as you're approaching the earth leaving the basement
我知道你们已经有很多贡献者了。
Yeah, we have a lot of contributors already.
是的，我们有很多贡献者了。
So the easiest way to stay in touch is go to this Twitter handle adds vite_js
最简单的保持联系的方法是去Twitter，vite_js 就是我们的账号。
Unfortunately,
不幸的是
No underscore version has already taken what their product.
没有下划线的版本已经存在了
yeah,
是的
And so vitejs we have already have a lot of contributors and get help feel free to.
Vite 已经有了很多贡献者，大家可以来寻求帮助。
Oh,
哦
also we have this chat.vitejs.dev
我们还有一个 chat.vitejs.dev
that's our Discord server.
那是我们的 Discord 社区
So if you want to join this later,
如果你以后想加入
I didn't realize Discord was allowing domains.
我不知道 Discord 还能配置这样的域名。
This is just a custom redirect.
这是我们的网址重定向。
OK,
好吧
yeah,
是的
So chat.vitejs.dev
chat.vitejs.dev
You get an automatic invite into our Discord server.
你会自动被邀请进入我们的 Discord 社区。
And that's a pretty cool community going on there.
这里有很酷。
Yeah,
是的
and that's pretty much it.
差不多了
well,
好吧
I appreciate your time Evan and walk into this.
非常感谢尤雨溪带来的直播，
I think it's a really good,
我觉得真的很好
and I hope you definitely pick up on the live streaming game folks have,
我希望你一定会注意到那些直播游戏的人
if you have enjoyed this,
如果你喜欢
you could actually find Evan.
你可以找到 Evan
He has a Twitter or sorry.
他有推特或抱歉
Here's a Twitter,
是有 Twitter
but he also has a Twitch.
但是他也有 Twitch
So what you mentioned your twitch is different.
你的 Twitch 用户名和 Twitter 一样吗
It's a different than what's on the screen?
和屏幕上的是一样的吗
Twitch is the same.
是一样的
OK,
好吧
so everybody to follow Evan on Twitch to make sure whenever he goes live,
大家都要关注 Twitch 确保他每次直播的时候，
showing some some code,
在展示一些代码时候，
you definitely don't want to miss it,
不会错过。
and if you are interested in learning about more projects,
如果你有兴趣了解更多的项目
definitely follow the channel Open Source Friday we do have a Meetup group for notification reasons,
关注 Open Source Friday，我们会有通知。
and I also live stream,
我也会做直播
so my name is here bdougieYO that who I am.
我的名字就在下面，我是 bdougieYO。
I do a lot of Github actions work,
我做了很多 GitHub Actions 的工作
which i didn't actually shout out my new t-shirt
我还没展示这个T恤。
It's they get up shop at the moment to you,
这是给你们准备的
so get it before it sold out,
趁着还有货赶紧买
and with that,
与此同时
I think we can go and in the stream,
我想我们结束直播了，
so thanks everybody.
谢谢大家
Thank you.
谢谢。